<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The wicked petition, or, Israel's sinfulness in asking a king explain'd in a sermon at the assizes held at Northampton, March the 1st, 1680/1 / by Fr. Giffard.</title>
            <author>Giffard, Francis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42720</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G690</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R195</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12181248</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12181248</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55656</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42720)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55656)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 762:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The wicked petition, or, Israel's sinfulness in asking a king explain'd in a sermon at the assizes held at Northampton, March the 1st, 1680/1 / by Fr. Giffard.</title>
                  <author>Giffard, Francis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Dring ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Perhaps by the Francis Giffard who was incorporated M.A. at Oxford 1660 cf. Anthony Wood. Fasti Oxonienses.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Samuel, 1st, XII, 17 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55656:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55656:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Wicked Petition, OR Iſrael's Sinfulneſs IN <hi>Asking a KING.</hi> Explain'd in A SERMON At the ASSIZES held at <hi>Northampton, March</hi> the <hi>1<hi rend="sup">ſt.</hi>
               </hi> 1680/1. By <hi>Fr. Giffard,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Dring,</hi> at the <hi>Harrow</hi> in <hi>Fleet-Street,</hi> near <hi>Chancery-Lane-End,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:55656:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55656:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO Thomas Ward Eſq; High Sheriff of the County of <hi>NORTHAMPTON.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>DRawn by your Commands from my poor but quiet ſhade into the open Sun, I ſhould be affraid it would be too bright and too hot for me, if I was not aſſured of the advantages of a ſhade from your luſtres. You ſhine with the Rays of a generous integrity in all your references which way ſoever they point, particularly that Publick Office which you now bear you have managed with ſo Noble and Powerful à light of Loyalty to your great Maſter, and of Equity, Diſcretion, Goodneſs, and Honour towards all, that the evil eyes which ſome diſaffected to His Majeſtie's Government have caſt upon you, have thereby been dazzled, and had their Malignant beams, when they could meet with nothing unbecoming in you to fix upon, with no little vexation reflected upon themſelves, upon their own unworthineſs and untowardneſs. The only Cloud by which you could be thought to ſuffer was made for an hour by my Blacks in the Pulpit. And I acknowledge that your Glories when lookt upon through me, muſt have a faint aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect. You might have had enow who would have ſerv'd you in my place with better and more agreeable Skill, none with honeſter Deſign. My De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign was to promote that fear of God which lies in the fearing and honouring of the King, that which I knew would be Satisfactory to you and to all other good Men. To which purpoſe I undertook for my Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject a Text of Scripture which the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlearned have wreſted to a far diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Senſe, and I wiſh they may ſo repent, that they may not do it alſo to their own Deſtruction. Whether I left (as I have been accuſed) ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my Text, or (conſidering the juncture of Affairs) my Auditory, I leave the unprejudiced to judge. Indeed as the Iſraelites were wicked
<pb facs="tcp:55656:3"/>in their manner of asking a King, not in the matter that they askt, I might alſo be faulty in my manner of handling their wickedneſs; but I dare affirm I was not in the matter which I thereupon aſſerted. Not Art, but Truth was my Buſineſs. And what if ſome were ſtung, ſwell'd and opened their Mouths? It was becauſe Truth met cloſely with very much vitiated intelligence and humour. That this may appear, what I Preach't I have Printed, without either Subſtraction or Addition; without Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction, becauſe what I ſaid I am ready to defend; without Addition, becauſe I would have ſome Reſerves for Defence in caſe of Aſſault. But here give me leave to add that Prayer for the King, which I then forgot in winding up my Diſcourſe, which <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſays, The Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians always uſed for the Emperors, and in which I aſſure my ſelf you and all other his truly Chriſtian Subjects will joyn, that he may have <hi>Vitam prolixam, imperium ſecurum, domum tutam, exercitus fortes, Senatum fidelem, populum probum, orbem quietum, quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> hominis &amp; Caeſaris vota ſunt:</hi> urging it ſo much farther, That if he ſhould not have <hi>Senatum: fidelem</hi> and <hi>populum probum,</hi> yet he may not miſs of having <hi>exercitus fortes,</hi> that ſo no diſloyalty, no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, no ſeditious or rebellious practiſings may be able to hinder him from having <hi>Vitam prolixam, imperium ſecurum, domum tutam,</hi> &amp;c. And this alſo, that whereas St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſays <hi>Regum eſt, non eſſe ſine comitum obſequio,</hi> he may have neither <hi>Comitem</hi> nor <hi>Vice-Comitem</hi> nor <hi>Comitatum,</hi> which does not eſteem this obſequiouſneſs to him their Duty, and ſtudy to perform it. As for your ſelf, who will never fail of doing ſo, my Prayer is that you may live long to be, as you are, a very excellent and influential Exemplar of Allegiance to your Prince, and of ſuch other Vertues as are ſuitable to your Character, and the Complexion of your Concerns. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Obliged, and moſt humble Servant</hi> Fr. Giffard.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55656:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Samuel 12.17. part of the Verſe.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>—That you may perceive and ſee, that your wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is great which you have done in the ſight of the Lord in asking you a King.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WAs there in reality no ſuch thing as right or wrong, but they were meerly the Comments of Politick, Romantick, ſuſpitious or feveriſh heads (of which yet the Imagination is abominable to a Sober Mind) Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would be moſt acceptable to Mankind in regard of that calm, eaſie, beauteous, pleaſant, ſafe, harmonious, uſeful ſtate of things, which it is its Nature to beget, nouriſh and maintain; and becauſe Anarchy would haſtily turn all the habitable Parts of the Earth into moſt inhoſpitable Scenes of confuſion, horrour, miſery: So that the more a man ſhould have of Senſe and Reaſon, that is, the more he ſhould be a man, the more obnoxious would he be to the feeling of what is moſt grievous.</p>
            <p>But they who without having their Spirits pre-engaged by Principles of Licentiouſneſs, will make a careful ſearch, will quickly find that there is Equity why there ſhould be rule among Men, in regard both of Man and God.</p>
            <p>It is altogether contrary to Eſſence, eſpecially if intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and free, to make or ſuffer any deficiency from it ſelf, and the glories of Humane Eſſence demand it as an Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Debt to their Merit to be held as dear as they are fair, and to be made as much of as they are great. Whereupon it is manifeſt that every man hath both a right and an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to live according to Nature, (in which <hi>Tully</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55656:4"/>with great reaſon places the happineſs of Man) and this in a way of amicable and beneficial Society: eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that man is variouſly enricht with Powers and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of delightful, profitable, kind, fruitful, juſt, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, holy, Converſes; of which it cannot eaſily be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined that they ſhould be a part of his Nature, and the uſe of them not be natural, that he ſhould have them to no other purpoſe than that they might be defeated, and ſo on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fit him for diſſatisfaction and calamity. The Capacities indeed and Neceſſities which Man hath of leading a Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal life are ſo many, great, important, evident, that he who hath common Intelligence and diſowns them, deſerves for his Puniſhment to loſe all the advantageous uſes of the one, and feel all the funeſt conſequences of the other. And there needs no other proof, that man is (what all ſober Philoſophy has named him) a creature of Society, but thoſe his mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Imbecillities, which according to the ordinary method of the World, inevitably betray him, when deſolate of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane aſſiſtance, to the invaſion of innumerable and inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable Evils. But now though the particular rights of Nature, by which Society is to be model'd, ſo as to be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſerviceable to Man's felicity, are fundamentally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd to men in the complexion of their own Eſſence, and though they are not altogether either unlegible or unpracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, yet withal they are not to be underſtood without far more ſtudy than the moſt of People are either able or willing to beſtow upon them, nor to be obſerv'd without a much greater ſubjection of Affection, Humour and Fancy to true Reaſon and Equity than is generally in Vogue through the World. If therefore it be of Humane concern, that thoſe rights ſhould be followed, and that Ignorance, Violence and Wickedneſs ſhould not prevail againſt them, it is of the ſame concern that the generality of people ſhould not be leſt to their own guidance, but be under Diſcipline for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55656:4"/>the regulation of their Minds and manners in the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them. More yet than ſo, the rights of Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture have by their proper worth and excellency, a very fair and well aſſured Title to be publickly declared, injoyned, maintained and vindicated. I ſay vindicated, and I mean among other things by chaſtiſing of Offenders againſt them, and that not only for prevention of what may follow, but alſo in recompence of what is paſt; becauſe, if the Fault which may be committed, calls for Puniſhment, much more does that which hath been, and becauſe it is indeed equita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly due to thoſe amiable rights, that ſo far as any Man acts contrary to them ſo far he ſhould have no benefit by them, but be treated as one who hath caſt them off, that he who has endeavour'd to make them void to others, ſhould have them made ſo by others to him; but this by a Political procedure, in regard it is a Political of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. To this purpoſe, as every man hath rights, and much more Societies of Men, which have a good claim to be adjuſted, preſerv'd and reveng'd; ſo ſome men have a peculiar right, which requires that they ſhould be obey'd in adjuſting, preſerving, and revenging of them. Such are all they who have a right of Soveraign Authority, and ſuch a right Men may have by Nature, by Purchaſe, by Conqueſt, by Donation, by Lot, by Divine Appointment, and it may be, by Election, Obligation, Merit, and other ways; and that there ſhould be ſome who have ſuch a right, God has been engaged to provide by the perfect reaſonableneſs of the thing, by his goodneſs to Man, and by his juſtice to himſelf.</p>
            <p>It was God who framed Man in ſuch a Conſtitution, that he was nobly and beautifully qualified for Society, was by a powerful inclination carried to it, had a plentiful harveſt of Emoluments offer'd him by it, and could not well be without it; ſo that in his Integrity, in Paradice, in his Lordſhip over all the Creatures of Earth, Air, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55656:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Sea, there was wanting a meet-help to him: and it was God who therefore alſo built Woman to keep Man Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny her ſelf, and to be alſo a means together with him to encreaſe and propagate Humane Society. But Society can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand in any tolerable faſhion without Government, and to oblige a Man to the one without the other, is no better than to Condemn him to the Company of Wolves, Bears, Lions, of incurable diſorder and miſchief. It was God therefore farther (God who is Love and Wiſdom it ſelf) who by the ſame primaeve Method that he took order for Society among Men, did likewiſe for Government among them, creating only one Man, and appointing all Mankind to come out of him. Government then of Man over Man, appears to be an Ordinance of God, as being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd in that meaſure of Humane Eſſence which he firſt ſet on foot by Creation, and ſet up again by Redemption, as a principal part of it, and as being morally and rationally ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the carrying on of the whole: but this as with great reſpect to Humane Intereſts, ſo with unſpeakably greater to the Divine; for all that Men have of good, or worthy in their being more God's than their own, becauſe they themſelves are ſo, and being both the Product and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of his Goodneſs and Wiſdom, and all their rights be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Derivatives and Inſtitutions of that Eternal reaſon and equity which lives in his Eſſence, they ought as ſuch to be moſt diligently cheriſh't and aſſerted; which, it is apparent cannot be done without Government. Farther, Man is bound to God in incomputable and uneſtimable ſcores: but rarely would, or indeed could one farthing thereof be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, much leſs paid, except there were ſome whoſe buſineſs it is to conduct the Affair. Now the rights and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of God are of inimaginably more value than the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Eſtates and Lifes of Men, than all the Univerſe beſides, and all others are to them no more than the duſt of the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance to unexaminable weight.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:55656:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Upon ſuch and many other Conſiderations, well might <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſay, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt.</hi> l. 1. Polit.</note> 
               <hi>To govern and to be governed are of the number both of neceſſary things, and of thoſe alſo that are profitable.</hi> Julius Caeſar, as <hi>Dion Caſſius</hi> gives us his words,<note place="margin">Dion Caſſ. <hi>l. 41.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>"Nature hath inſtituted among men the neceſſary and beneficial things of governing and being go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned, and it is impoſſible without theſe that any thing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhould endure for any time whatever.</hi> And <hi>Tully,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tull. <hi>l. 3.</hi> De Legibus.</note> Nihil porro tam aptum eſt ad jus conditionem<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> naturae (quod cùm dico legem à me dici, nihil aliud intelligi volo) quam imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, ſine quo nec domus ulla, nec civitas nec gens, nec ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum univerſum genus ſtare, nec rerum Natura omnis nec ipſe mundus poteſt.</p>
            <p>With theſe three fam'd Secretaries of Humane Wiſdom, have all, though of very common obſervation, found reaſon to agree. The Queſtion is not whether there ſhould be any Government but what Government there ſhould be; a Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion which hath been moſt fiercely debated with Tongue, Pen and Sword. To come to our Text, the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and all their Elders were for Monarchy, They askt a King <hi>Samuel</hi> on the other ſide at leaſt ſeems to have been againſt it, <hi>Now therefore,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſtand and ſee this great thing which the Lord will do before your eyes. Is it not wheat-harveſt to day? I will call upon the Lord, and he ſhall ſend thunder and rain, that you may perceive and ſee that your wickedneſs is great, which you have done in the ſight of the Lord in asking you a King.</hi> And he made good his word, as we find in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel of the Chapter.</p>
            <p>That we now may perceive and ſee wherein this great wickedneſs lay of which <hi>Samuel</hi> arraigned them in our Text, and they confeſt themſelves guilty in the 19 <hi>v.</hi> of the Chapter,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55656:6"/>Let us take a view firſt of the Circumſtances which their Petition (if I may call it ſo) had retaining to it. Secondly, of the thing it ſelf, which they Petition'd for.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt of the Circumſtances for Petitions, though for things in their own Nature good, may be ſo circumſtantiated as highly to deſerve abhorrence. And, if I miſtake not, there were ſeveral things which conſpired to render this ſo.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, They hereby arrogated to themſelves a higher Conduct of the Publick than belonged to them. It is true they were the Elders of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that preſented it, and ſo they were Stars of a more than ordinary Magnitude, elevation and influence in the State; but to rule the day of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was no part of their Commiſſion. Notwithſtanding the Authority of all the Elders of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and particularly of that chief Council or Senate of them, which we call the <hi>Sanhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drim,</hi> inſtituted by God at the requeſt of <hi>Moſes</hi> for his aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, when that celebrated Lawgiver was to lay down the chief management of the Publick: not but at his All powerful Maſter's command, and together with his life, he was ſo far from leaving it to them as their right, or as proper to them, that he addreſt himſelf to God with this Prayer, <hi>Let the Lord the God of the ſpirits of all fleſh ſet a man over the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 27.16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>which may go out before them, and which may go in before them, and which may lead them out, and which may bring them in, that the Congregation of the Lord be not as ſheep, that have no Shepheard.</hi> Which certainly would have been very injuriouſly ſaid, had <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. the chief guidance of the flock lain either in the whole flock themſelves, or in the Elders thereof, had he not believed that they would have been as Sheep that had no Shepheard, unleſs beſide the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Shepheards of the Congregation, there was one who was Maſter of them all. In relation to the King of our Text, I reckon it chiefly, if not only, was that God ſaid to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Hoſea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 8.4.</note> concerning the People of <hi>Iſrael, They have ſet up
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55656:6"/>Kings, but not by me.</hi> The <hi>Arabick</hi> Verſion of which is to this ſence, <hi>They have reigned from themſelves, not from me.</hi> God's meaning here ſeems to be, They have aſſumed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed ſoveraign Empire as of right pertaining to them, and have ſet up Regal Government, and given Inveſtiture of it upon pretenſions of an Authority founded in themſelves of chooſing what Government and Governours they have a mind to, without having any reſpect to my appointment of Monarchy, or to my right of inaugurating into it whom I thought fit, But I know not how God could have ſpoken this by way of Accuſation as he does, if there had been lodged in them a right of the Supreme management of the Nation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But Secondly, in thoſe words of <hi>Hoſea</hi> there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more implied of Fault in the Petition of our Text, namely, that they askt a King without asking God's advice, whether or no it was agreeable to his Will. Wherefore alſo God adds there, <hi>they have made Princes, but I knew it not.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 8.4.</note> The <hi>Targum</hi> of <hi>Jonathan Ben <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ziel</hi> upon <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.15. is to this effect, <hi>Ye ſhall ſeek inſtruction of the Lord, and after that ſhall ſet a King over you.</hi> The Supreme Arbitrement of all Affairs is ſo illuſtriouſly God's Prerogative, that he who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies it, muſt neceſſarily be concluded to have either a head of monſtrous default, or a heart moſt malignantly affected. Conſidering which, and that there can nothing occur, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the buſineſs of Government, which is both the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance and Miniſtry of God, they ſhould in this matter chiefly have been of the Heathen's Mind, though not as a Heathen,<note place="margin">Cicero <hi>in</hi> Orat. pro domo ſua ad Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices.</note> 
               <hi>Caput eſſe interpretari quae deorum immortalium vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas eſſe videatur.</hi> Nor had he left them without his Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, Prophets, and Prieſts to inform them. But did they not, as too many among us, reckon the Seers blind in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with themſelves, or proper to be conſulted only in ſuch concerns, as <hi>Saul</hi> came to <hi>Samuel</hi> about when that of the Text was on foot, loſt Aſſes? The Prieſts to have their hearts
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55656:7"/>and heads too much heated with the fires of the Altar at which they ſerv'd to be of their Counſel, ſit only to receive rules from them, not give to them? did they not take meaſures from ſome of thoſe Idols, which had been former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worſhip'd among them: from <hi>Berith,</hi> the Leaguing and Covenanting Deity, as the word ſignifies? from <hi>Baal,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which name <hi>Nimrod</hi> was worſhip'd, that is the Rebel, as his name denotes? from <hi>Aſtaroth</hi> the Moon, that Queen of Changes both in her own and other Bodies?</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is certain Thirdly, That they hereby negotiated a great change in the Government; which, like the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of a Noble Structure from one foundation to another, or rather like the altering of its whole frame and conveigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, not only creates abundance of trouble and diſorder, but alſo commonly draws after it conſequences far more to be abhorred than deſired, and which therefore has no paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble excuſe, but plain and abſolute Neceſſity. Beſides they hereby teſtified themſelves diſcontent with their preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, though very ſatisfactory, and alſo of a light and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant humour; whereas to be given to change, eſpecially in the affairs of Religion and Polity, ſpeaks both a weakneſs in their minds who are ſo, and a diſagreeableneſs to God's, with whom is no variableneſs nor ſhadow of turning and not only keeps them like the rowling Stone naked of all the moſſe of good acquiſts, but alſo expoſes them at the beſt to be by degrees worne away, oftentimes to be ſuddenly broken in pieces.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They were herein moſt unthankfully; contumeliouſly and rebelliouſly traiterous both unto their chief Magiſtrate, and to God whoſe Miniſter he was. <hi>Samuel</hi> had recover'd out of the hands of the Philiſtins, not only all the Cities and Coaſts of <hi>Iſrael</hi> which they had taken, but alſo the glory of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Ark of God; he had relieved them from thoſe their grievous Oppreſſors, ſo that they were kept under
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55656:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>hatches all his days; he had brought to a Peace with them their powerful Enemies the <hi>Amorites;</hi> he had re-eſtabliſht the true Worſhip of God, and had reclaim'd the People from their abominable Errours to a fair uniformity therein; he had every year ridden in Circuit among them to do them juſtice; in ſum, having now ſat at the Helm, as I reckon, ſomewhat above Twenty years, he had all the while ſteer'd the Nation with moſt induſtrious, laborious, equitable and pious endeavours for their happineſs, and thoſe ſucceſsful al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, though when he took the Rudders, the Ship was in very ill condition. Having now by taking pains for their wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and God's honour exhauſted and worn out himſelf, ſo that he was grown old before length of days had made him ſo (for, if I miſtake not, he was not yet Threeſcore years of age) ſo that his Silver hairs were the Enſigns of rich and glorious toils, and his wrinkles the Skars of honourable fatigues, the thanks and recompence they gave him was to thruſt him out of the Seat of Judicature, as one of no value, and unfit to hold it; and this, though they could not upon his challenge but clear him from every thing of Injuſtice and Arbitrary acting, and alſo very well know that God had placed him there. But they who caſt off thoſe whom God hath appointed to Rule over them, do in the ſame act caſt off God himſelf.<note place="margin">Num. 16.11. Num. 26.9.</note> 
               <hi>Corah</hi> and his Company that roſe up againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> are therefore ſaid to have gather'd themſelves together and ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven againſt God, and that, though there were of their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Two hundred and Fifty Princes of the Aſſembly, famous in the Congregation, Men of renown. <hi>Simplicius,</hi> if I have not forgotten, tells us of the <hi>Achorites,</hi> who were ſwallow'd up of the Earth for denying God: I cannot but think they were the <hi>Corites,</hi> (with the Article prefixt) and ſaid to deny God becauſe they rebell'd againſt his Vicegerent and his High Prieſt, That our Petitioners in caſting off <hi>Samuel,</hi> caſt off God alſo, God himſelf declares, when he ſays to <hi>Samuel,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55656:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>They have not rejected thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 8 7.</note> 
               <hi>but they have rejected me, that I ſhould not reign over them.</hi> But yet there is more than that contained in thoſe words; namely, that they reprobated God in regard of his own Government over them as well as of <hi>Samuel</hi>'s, and dealt no better with him than with his Lord Lieutenant. God had moſt benignly undertaken to be their King in a more than common way, in a more particular man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner than he was of all the world beſides, and it could not be thought that he had no other right of being ſo, but what was derived from the People, or was capable of loſing it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had entred into Covenant with them; and in the exerciſe of this his Kingſhip he had done them ſo many and great acts of Grace, as it is impoſſible to begin an eſtimation of, and yet by this Petition they not only moſt impiouſly derogated from his Goodneſs, Care, Juſtice, and Wiſdom in his oeconomy of them, as if he was unmindful and negligent of the Publick weal, and underſtood not how to manage it without their advice, but went about moſt execrably to put him out of his Throne. So we may partly ſee by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd place, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.7; but more by what is ſaid 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. where <hi>Samuel</hi> having reaſoned to them of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſes and benefits which God had performed to them, adjoyns <hi>Verſe</hi> the 12. <hi>And when he ſaw that Nahaſh the King of the Children of Ammon came againſt you, ye ſaid unto me, Nay, but a King ſhall reign over us, when the Lord your God was your King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Theſe words offer to us a fifth Particular of their wickedneſs; <hi>viz.</hi> That notwithſtanding the many Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances which they had received from God, and ſeveral of them by the hand of <hi>Samuel,</hi> out of fears of a Neighbour Prince, they moſt vilifyingly diſcarded the Conduct of them both, for another refuge.</p>
            <p n="6">6. They herein went upon the track of their former Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Defections. Practiſes of Rebellion, as ſoon as of any
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55656:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>other Sin, nurſe themſelves into diſpoſitions, diſpoſitions into habits, and the fire of theſe, though it ought to be with all poſſible care extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht, ſeldom wholly is; but though it may be for a while cover'd, cooled or pent up, commonly glows under its own aſhes, and erelong revives and breaks out again into a more furious and ravaging flame. To have and to do as they liſt, is ſo connatural to Mankind by dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neracy, that they hate nothing more than to be under reſtraint, though by God himſelf. A juſt Subjection therefore they name Slavery, and the drawing back from it they aſcribe to generoſity of Spirit. And if any other Nation (I was going to ſay except our own) was guilty of this refractory and perfidious humour of revolting this of the <hi>Jews</hi> was. So that rather than endure that yoke of Government which God put upon them, they would have one of their own putting on, though more ſtrict and ſevere. According to the habitualneſs hereof to them, did they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have themſelves in the preſent affair, not conſidering that ſuch Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents were ſo far from deſerving to be made leading rules, much more from having any Plea to be lookt upon as Laws, that they could no way be expiated but by declaring their hearty repentance and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of them. <hi>According to all the works,</hi> ſays God to <hi>Samuel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 8.8.</note> 
               <hi>which they have done ſince the day that I brought them out of Egypt even unto this day, wherewith they have forſaken me and ſerved other Gods, ſo do they alſo to thee.</hi> Their revolting from their Prince, was Siſter to their defection from God. <hi>Theodorick</hi> had in his Court a Miniſter whom he very much loved. He thinking to pleaſe his Prince, left the Doctrine of Chriſt's eternal conſubſtantial Deity, and proteſted himſelf of the <hi>Arrian</hi> Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, wherewith he knew him infected: but his Maſter hearing of it cauſed his Head to be ſtricken off, ſaying, That he who had not kept his Faith with God, would never be loyal to a Mortal Man.</p>
            <p n="7">7. But ſeventhly, Our Petitioners were not herein like themſelves only, but alſo were carried to it by a fond Zeal of being like the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour States, without conſidering whether it was good or bad, which they had a paſſion to be like them in. They who devote themſelves to write after the Copy of another man's manners at all adventure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an eye to its goodneſs, and far more likely to do what is evil than what is good; and if they happen to do what is good, they do it not well, becauſe they do it not out of a ſtudy of goodneſs, have furtendred their reaſon and their duty to the Copy, and act not the Man, but the Ape Farther, He that will blindly follow the blind, may poſſibly make a few fair and advantageous ſteps, but ſhall nevertheleſs be reckoned a Fool or Madman, becauſe it is meerly by chance, not any good-cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55656:9"/>that he does ſo, and becauſe he throws himſelf into a moſt certain danger of falling into the Ditch. The States whom our Elders ſtudied to be like, were not only blind, but alſo of ſuch wicked and pernicious manners, eſpecially in things pertaining to God, as ſhould have made them wary of being like them in any thing, much more ſhould have kept them from making it their buſineſs to be like them. And they muſt neceſſarily be eſteemed to do wickedly, who, though they do what is in its ſelf good, do it not upon that account, but out of a precipitate imitation of wicked Men.</p>
            <p n="8">8. They took a Pretext for doing it from faults of Publick impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance committed by ſome great Officers of the Government. <hi>Samuel</hi> having made his two Sons the Aſſiſtants of his Age in the Judicature of the Nation,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 8.3.</note> they <hi>turned aſide after lucre, took bribes, and perverted judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> and for this reaſon their excellent Father muſt be depoſed, God himſelf revolted from, and another mode of Government brought in: A piece of wickedneſs certainly, weighed againſt which that of <hi>Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi>'s Sons will not ſtir the ballance. Muſt the Sun be tumbled from his Saphire Throne, loſe his golden Crown of Rays, and Empire of the Day, becauſe his light is ſometimes intercepted by Clouds which he himſelf draws up. But ſuppoſe <hi>Samuel</hi> accuſed of Male-adminiſtration in his own perſon, who made the People judge over him whom God had made judge over them? God having conſtituted him Supreme Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour in all Cauſes over the People next and immediately under him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, could there among the ſame People be a Superior to him between him and God? This colour of ill-government the ambitious <hi>Abſolom</hi> made uſe of againſt his Royal Father, and having by that and other inſinuating Pretences and Courtſhips ſtolen away from him the hearts of the People and their Elders, procured him to be reprobated by them from the Throne, and himſelf advanced into it; But it lyes obvious to every eye, that he who was the Lord's Anointed, though guilty of Crimes puniſhable by Death in another Perſon, had right on his ſide againſt him who was the People's Anointed, though a Pretender to Juſtice and Piety, and that Divine Juſtice ſet a remark upon the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize of the latter, as moſt wicked, bringing to a fatal end by the treachery of his own head, him who was a Traitor to his Political head, of whoſe Body alſo he was a beloved and famous part.</p>
            <p n="9">9. They were over-haſty in their Petition. They left not their great Monarch to his own time, but inſolently preſcribed to him theirs. God intended them a King, but was not willing that his Favourit and Vice-Roy <hi>Samuel</hi> ſhould loſe his ſeat of Soveraign Judicature, but for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55656:9"/>the grave and a Throne in Heaven, or that the Scepter ſhould be put into any hand until <hi>David</hi>'s was made fit to change the Sheephook for it. He who importunely urges the performance of what he deſires with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtaying his leiſure upon whom he depends for it, may poſſibly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive what he asks, and at his own hour, but not without deſerving, if not incurring the diſpleaſure of his Benefactour.</p>
            <p n="10">10. It was not ſo much a Petition, as an Impudent, Peremptory, and obſtinate demand; they went to their Prince's face, and required him to come down from the Seat of Authority in which God had inſtalled him, make an alteration of it, and put another into it; and though both he and God himſelf declared themſelves diſpleaſed with their proceedings, they contumaciouſly perſiſted in them, and told him they would have what they deſired.</p>
            <p>The Son has a right of Petitioning his Father, but not of doing it uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, unadviſedly, ungratefully, opprobriouſly, treaſonably, rebelliouſly, in imitation of bad Neighbours, out of an unſtable mind, a revolting inclination, and a ruling deſign, with the terms of Empire, a forehead of Braſs, and a neck of an Iron Sinew.</p>
            <p>In theſe reſpects the wickedneſs in the Text was great, and it was farther greatned by the generality of it. In ſuch a caſe many hands make not light but heavy work, and in this there were none who had either ſo much conſideration of their Duty as to abhor what was done, or ſo much courage as to declare they did ſo.</p>
            <p>Theſe are Circumſtances which manifeſtly contributed to the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs in the Text. There are ſome alſo which probably did ſo. It is indeed likely that there lay at the bottom ambitious, covetous, malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, licentious and other ſuch ſiniſter regards. Some might hope to obtain, rather than deſerve, if not the Throne which they were erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet ſome eminent ſtation near it, or gainful Office under it.</p>
            <p>Others might aim at being revenged for acts of Juſtice or Injuſtice done them. A third ſort might deſign Liberty of Religion with the overthrow of that which was eſtabliſht, which they knew <hi>Samuel</hi> was much more a Saint than to allow. A fourth might be emported, though very groundleſly and unjuſtly, with umbrages that their preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour had intentions of Arbitrary and Tyrannick Rule by himſelf, or Sons, or both.</p>
            <p>But theſe particulars not being certain, I ſhall forbear to urge them; and having ſhewn enow that are certain, and certainly wicked, I ſhall now come to conſider whether the matter of the demaild of the Text made it not alſo wicked in its own Nature,</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:55656:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="1">1. The Matter of it was a King. Let us then, Firſt, ſee what a King was; and to that purpoſe let us view in the firſt place how he is repreſented by the ancient <hi>Myſtae</hi> of Phiſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, Hiſtory and Policy among the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Suid.</hi> in <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Kingship is an uncontroulable Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> are the words of a Writer in <hi>Suidas,</hi> whom he names not,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dion Chryſ.</hi> in Orat. 3. de regno.</note> but whom I dare name a Heathen. <hi>Dion Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtomus</hi> hath the ſame words; and more: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſays he, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; Kingſhip is an uncontroulable Government, and the Law is the King's Decree. <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his ſhort Treatiſe concerning Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, Democracy and Oligarchy, calls the firſt <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Kingly Government, and ſays once that it is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>of abſolute Authority,</hi> twice <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>uncontroulable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dion Caſſius</hi> ſays of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors,<note place="margin">Dion Caſſ. <hi>l. 53.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>They have the name of Emperour throughout, in ſignification of their full and perfect Authority, inſtead of the title of King, and Dictator.</hi> And again, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>They are ſet looſe from the Laws, as the Latine words themſelves ſpeak; that is, they are free from all neceſſary ſubjection to Law or Coaction by it, and are bound by none of the written Inſtitutes.</hi> Having alſo ſaid, that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>they were inveſted with all the power of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> He adjoins, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſo that they had all things of Kings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt.</hi> in libris Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litic.</note> 
               <hi>except their unacceptable title. Ariſtotle</hi> having ſet down five forts of Regal Government, he ſays of the Fifth which is named by him <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>perfect Regal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> that it is chiefly or moſt properly called Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, that Tyrannie is the Corruption of it, that it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55656:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>when one man is Lord of all;</hi> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>by which the King governs all according to his will:</hi> and that it is the ſame kind of Government with that of the Father or Maſter of a Family: Of the four others, which he ſays were <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>according to Law,</hi> and eſpecially the <hi>Lacedaemonian,</hi> (which, as is agreed by all, was almoſt wholly a mixture of Ariſtocracy and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocracy), he ſays that they are not properly any kind of Kingdom or Polity. <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> ſays in <hi>Dion Caſſius,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">In Excerp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis <hi>Dionis Caſſii.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>of Imperial Authority God only may be Judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Athenians</hi> accounted themſelves, and are accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Writers to have diſſolved Kingly Government in ſetting up the Archontick, which was of one man who was liable to be controuled and called to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diologenes,</hi> a <hi>Pythagoran,</hi> ſays in <hi>Stobaeus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diologenes</hi> apud <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baeum</hi> in Serm. 46.</note> 
               <hi>A King, having an uncontrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable Authority, and being himſelf an animated Law, hath the form of God among Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ecphantas,</hi> one of the ſame Sect, hath in the ſame Author theſe words, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stob.</hi> Ser. 46.</note> 
               <hi>It belongs alſo to a King, to rule himſelf, and to be ruled by none.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Otanes</hi> a <hi>Perſian</hi> Noble in <hi>Herodotus</hi> ſpeaking of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy or Kingly Government ſays, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Herod.</hi> l. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Which hath a right of doing whatever it will without controul.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:55656:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Caius Memmius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Saluſt</hi> in bello Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurthino.</note> a Tribune of the People ſays in <hi>Saluſt,</hi> Impunè quaelibet facere, id eſt regem eſſe; <hi>To do what a man will with Impunity, that is to be a King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cleopatra</hi> urging her <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> to call <hi>Herod</hi> to an account,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſep.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riq. l. 15.</note> he replyed, That it was not fair, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>To demand of a King an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of what was done in his Government; for ſo he would not be a King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Daughters of <hi>Danaus</hi> in <hi>Aeſchylus</hi> upon the common notion of Regal Authority tell the <hi>Argive</hi> King,</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>—<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aeſchyl.</hi> in Suppl.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou art the City, thou the People art,</l>
                  <l>Being a Governour not to be judg'd.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Kingly Authority is in the <hi>Antigona</hi> of <hi>Sophocles,</hi> called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>perfect Monarchy.</hi> And in the ſame Tragedy <hi>Creon</hi> ſaying to <hi>Aemon,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Is not the City his eſteem'd that Reigns?</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>He rejoins, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>fairly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall add no more of this, though I could ſpend many hours upon it, ſave that of <hi>Horace.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Regum timendorum in proprios greges,</l>
               <l>Reges in ipſos imperium eſt Jovis.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hor.</hi> li. Carn. 3. Od. 1.</note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>But this is Heathen Doctrine: Let us try how agreeable it is to the Theology of Scripture. And here</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:55656:11"/>
            <p>Wee need look no farther than to what <hi>Samuel</hi> ſays upon the Buſineſs of the Text; God having commanded <hi>Samuel</hi> to proteſt ſolemnly to the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 8.9.</note> and declare to them the manner (as we tranſlate it) of the King that ſhould Reign over them: The Judge ſays to them,<note place="margin">1 Sam 8.11.</note> 
               <hi>This will be the manner of the King that ſhall Reign over you; He will take your Sons, and appoint them for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, for his Chariots, and to be his Horſemen; and ſome ſhall run before his Chariots: And he will appoint him Captains over Thouſands, and Captains over Fifties; and to ear his Ground, and to reap his Harveſt, and to make his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of War, and Inſtruments of Chariots: And he will take your Daughters to be Confectionaries, and to be Cookes, and to be Bakers: And he will take your Fields, and your Vineyards, and your Olive yards, the beſt of them, and give them to his Servants: And he will take the Tenth of your Seed, and of your Vineyards, and give to his Officers, and to his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants: And he will take your Men-Servants, and your Maid-Servants, and your goodlieſt young Men, and your Aſſes, and put them to his Work: He will take the Tenth of your Sheep, and ye ſhall be his Servants.</hi> This I look upon as a Law: For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The word <hi>Miſhphat,</hi> which we tranſlate <hi>Manner,</hi> as the Learned know, properly ſignifies <hi>Right, Judgment, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute,</hi> and the like.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is in this Senſe rendred here, by all the Ancient Tranſlations, <hi>Arabick, Syriack, Vulgar Latine,</hi> that of the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> and the <hi>Chaldee</hi> Paraphraſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Theſe Words of <hi>Samuel,</hi> were either a Prediction from God only, of what the King would do, or a Law of what he might do: If only a Prediction, and not a Law, then all the Kings were Tyrants and Oppreſſors, <hi>David, Solomon, Aſa, Jehoſaphat, Jehoaſh, Amaziah, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah, Hezekiah, Joſiah;</hi> but of the good and Pious Reign of all theſe, the Holy Ghoſt gives very fair Elogies.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Theſe things appear to be not ſpoken by way of Prediction only, to deter the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from perſiſting in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55656:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>their Deſire of a King, becauſe ſuch frightful and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid things might have been ſaid upon that Subject, in compariſon with which theſe here ſpoken of, may well ſeem ſoft, pleaſant and deſireable.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Manner in which God commanded <hi>Samuel</hi> to declare theſe things to them, ſpeak it a Law; <hi>proteſting thou ſhalt proteſt to them, and ſhew them the Miſhphat of the King,</hi> ſays God, who calls his Law his Teſtimony.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Cloſe of it is drawn in the terms of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; <hi>And ye ſhall be his Servants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Samuel,</hi> after he had declared this to them, added, <hi>And ye ſhall cry out in that day, becauſe of your King, and the Lord will not hear you in that day.</hi> They would have had a Remedy in their Hands, when diſ-eaſed by their King, and ſick of him, if this had not been a Law.</p>
            <p n="8">8.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 10.25.</note> 
               <hi>Samuel</hi> wrote it in a Book, and laid it up before the Lord, that is, about the Arke, the place of which was in the Holy of Holyes, and in which were laid up the Pot of Manna, the Rod of <hi>Aaron,</hi> and the two Tables. So I conclude, becauſe when the Pot of Manna was commanded to be laid up before the Lord, <hi>Aaron</hi> laid it up before the Teſtimony.<note place="margin">Exod. 16 33.</note> Now ſurely, had it been on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Prediction of the Manner of the Kingdom, and not a Divine Law, it would not have been laid up with ſo much Tenderneſs, Reſpect and Valuation, more by far, than all the reſt of the Law of God, except the two Tables all that being only put into the Hands of the Prieſts and Elders. If any ſhall make any queſtion, Whether this <hi>Miſhphat</hi> in the Tenth Chapter, was the ſame with that in the Eighth, becauſe there it is called <hi>Of the King,</hi> here <hi>Of the Kingdom.</hi> I ſay, Firſt, the Ancient Jews, and other believed it to be the ſame: It is render'd in both places alike, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Right of the King,</hi> by the Seventy; by words which ſignifie <hi>the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the King,</hi> in the <hi>Chaldee</hi> Paraphraſe; <hi>the Right of the King,</hi> in the <hi>Syriack; the Rights of the King,</hi> in the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55656:12"/>
               <hi>Arabick</hi> Verſion. Secondly had this been a new Law of God, different from what had been ſpoken of before, <hi>Samuel</hi> would have declared here, as he did there, that he had received new Inſtructions from God about it. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, had it been a new Law, it would have been recited by <hi>Samuel,</hi> and recorded by him as that was.</p>
            <p>With Relation to this Law (though not as preſcribed to <hi>Iſrael</hi> only) I cannot but think it is that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays,<note place="margin">Ecleſ. 8.2.</note> 
               <hi>I counſel (or charge) thee to keep the Kings Commandment, and that in regard of the Oath of God.</hi> And that,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe that Law was delivered with a moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Proteſtation from God, which hath much of the Nature of an Oath.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe it was laid up with the Tables of the Covenant, and about the Ark of the Covenant, and the Law of God, hath the Name of the Covenant, and the Covenant which God in giving his Law, made with the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is called the Oath that he made with them</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Becauſe it is epitomized in the following Words of <hi>Solomon, He doth whatſoever pleaſeth him; where the word of a King is, there is Power, and who may ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him what doeſt thou?</hi> To this Queſtion of <hi>Solomon, Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> replies, No private Perſon, but the Magiſtrate or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate may. But I cannot but wonder, that he ſhould be ſuch a Novice in Learning, and Maſter in Impudence at the ſame time; ſo clear is the ſence of the Words by their own Light, as alſo by what <hi>Job</hi> ſays, <hi>Who ſhall ſay unto him, what doeſt thou?</hi> And by <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, he doth according to his Will,<note place="margin">Job 9.12.</note> and none can ſtay his Hand, or ſay unto him what doeſt thou?<note place="margin">Dan. 5.35.</note> Which they both ſpake to teſtify the Authority of God to be abſolutely Supreme and uncontroulable. So much there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of God was in the King, according to <hi>Solomon,</hi> that there was no Body, whoever of his People, no Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, no Senate to whom he was bound to give an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55656:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>This Senſe of <hi>Solomon</hi> we are prepar'd to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, by that Saying of his Father <hi>David,</hi> to God, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Head of his Adultery and Murther, <hi>Againſt thee on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have I ſinned.</hi> So he ſaid in the High Tide of his Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; and his Meaning is, that though his Sins were ſuch as were in others, to be puniſhed by the Judge, the Judge on Earth; yet as his, they were to be puniſhed only by the Judge of Heaven and Earth. This is the Expoſition which all the Ancient Fathers, and Learned Men, and ſome Famed Papiſts alſo give of the Words; which are more than I could now half quote, was that my whole Buſineſs here. It is indeed ſufficiently evident to them, who are not blind, or will not ſhut their Eyes, that the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were, of Right, free from all Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erſion, both by Elders and People. The Queſtion then will be, Whether other Kings had the ſame Prerogative? And it appears, they had, not only by Humane Records, which I muſt not now touch; but alſo by what is ſaid of the Affair of the Text, and by ſeveral Inſtances in Scripture. In the Concern of the Text, we find, that the People ſaid to <hi>Samuel, Make us a King to judge us like all the Nations;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam 8.5.</note> and that God commanded <hi>Samuel</hi> to hearken to their Voice in all that they had ſaid unto him.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 8.7.</note> But now they were not like other Nations in their Kings, if the Kings of other Nations had not ſuch a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority as I have ſhewn theirs had.</p>
            <p>Of the many Inſtances, I ſhall at preſent urge only one, and it ſhall be of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſeph</hi> was known in <hi>Egypt,</hi> to be of another Country and Religion, to have been bought by <hi>Potiphar,</hi> in the Quality of a Slave; and, after he had been raiſed, by his favor, to the management of all his buſineſs, to have been ſtrongly accus'd by his Wife, of attempting the Violation of their Bed; and thereupon to have lain long, and with much hardſhip in Priſon: Yet this Man, when not above thirty years of Age, upon the Interpretation of the King's Dream, concerning
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55656:13"/>ſeven Years of Plenty, and as many of Scarcity ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively; which, whether it was true or falſe, from a good Spirit or from a Bad, might then be doubted by ſome; and upon his Counſel to him, to ſet one over the Land, to make Proviſion againſt the Famine, in which he might be then ſuſpected to have ſome ambitious Regards to himſelf, did <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> without adviſing but with ſome of the Servants of his Court, conſtitute a Ruler both over his Houſe, and the whole Land;<note place="margin">Gen. 41.</note> and he ſet him in ſuch an elevated degree of Power, that only in the Throne was he himſelf greater, that the People were all to be ruled according to his Word; that without him, no Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was to lift up his Hand or Foot in all the Land; that he had it in his Commiſſion, to bind his Princes at his Pleaſure, and to teach his Senators Wiſdom; and that he might take, and lay up, what, and where he thought fit, of the Fruits of the Land, for the uſe, and under the Hand of his Maſter. This <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did, by vertue of his Regal Crown, ſo he declared by thoſe Words,<note place="margin">Gen. 41.44.</note> 
               <hi>I am Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh, and without thee ſhall no man lift up his Hand or Foot. Pharaoh</hi> being the Title of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Kings, as Kings, derived to them, as I could ſhew from the firſt King of <hi>Egypt, Miſraim</hi> the Son of <hi>Ham.</hi> And that herein he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended not his Scepter beyond its due Limits; I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reckon,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe <hi>Joſeph</hi> adviſes him to it, with the next Breath, after he had, by the Spirit of God, explained his Dream.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe <hi>Joſeph,</hi> who feared God, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accepted, but alſo exerciſed the Authority, and that in a great Latitude.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Becauſe <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſays, That God had made him Lord and Ruler of all <hi>Egypt,</hi> which he could not well have ſaid, if it had been unjuſt in <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to have made him ſo, it being by his Authority that he was ſo made.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:55656:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Fourthly, Becauſe <hi>David</hi> ſings of this Act of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> as a juſt Ground and Matter of Glorifying God. I ſhall only add to this, that the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> being, as all Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of them agree, a moſt unſtable, envious, proud, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious, furious People, and <hi>novarum rerum uſque ad pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licas cantilenas cupientes,</hi> it is not likely they would have ſubmitted herein to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> if they had not accounted that he herein exerciſed a juſt Prerogative. They in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſeem to have look'd upon their Natural Kings, as having a Paternal Right of Dominion: For that <hi>Apis,</hi> which I interpret Father, was the Name of one, at leaſt of their Primitive Kings; and alſo <hi>Pamyles</hi> or <hi>Palmys</hi> which ſignifies <hi>The King the Father,</hi> and that <hi>Abimeleck,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>The Father the King,</hi> and from which, <hi>Pamyles</hi> and <hi>Palmys,</hi> differ but with a little Change of Letters, was the Common Name of the Kings of the <hi>Philiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ins,</hi> who were Grand-Children of <hi>Miſraim,</hi> the firſt Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Thus do we ſee, That a King of Old, was a Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour abſolutely Supreme, not to be violently controul'd, or call'd to an Account by any of his People, but to be either actively, or paſſively obey'd.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us in the next place ſee, whether the asking of a King was not a Wickedneſs, conſidering it as to the Matter of it abſtractively in it ſelf; that indeed it was far from it, there are theſe Arguments among others, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd us by Scripture.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Condition in which God put Mankind, by the Creation, Flood, and Diſperſion at <hi>Babel,</hi> implyed Monarchy their Rightful Government, both for preſent and future Generations. For Man is the Head of the Woman, and ſhe ought to be in ſubjection to him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe was made after him, of him, and for him; ſhe came not into the World until Man was inthroned in the Dominion of all Inferior Creatures; ſhe was made of his Rib, and ſo was Bone of his Bone, and Fleſh of his Fleſh;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55656:14"/>and ſhe was made to be a Meet Help to him; ſo that he muſt have it in his Power to make her ſo. Beſides, he is of a more Elevated and Subſtantial Worth, and ſhe is the weaker Veſſel. This Reaſon, <hi>Tully</hi> tells us, was obſerv'd of Old,<note place="margin">Cic. in Orat. Pro <hi>L.</hi> Muraena.</note> 
               <hi>Mulieres omnes propter infirmitatem Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilii majores in tutorem poteſtate eſſe voluerunt,</hi> The Son owes Obedience to the Father, becauſe he owes his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him, and commonly many of the Advantages of it by his Education; and becauſe he is as much a part of him, as is his beſt Blood, as is any Member of his Body; the Son being the Father's Tranſcript, and having his Blood and Nature in him, particularly the Eldeſt Son, having his Blood and Nature firſt in him, being the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and Chief of his Strength, being next to him, and entring firſt into the Poſſeſſion of his Power; all the other Children, are, by Primitive Inſtitution, after the Father's Death, ſubject to the Eldeſt Brother; and conſequently, all of the ſame Blood to the Eldeſt of the Eldeſt Line of it. This Title of Primogeniture to rule, was anciently acknowledged by the Followers of Nature; <hi>Dicaearchus</hi> particularly, and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> ſpeak of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſay it was of Old in uſe in the Cities of <hi>Greece.</hi> But it is declared by God himſelf, in ſeveral places of Scripture, I ſhall inſtance on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in one, touching the firſt Firſt-born: When God ſaw him (I mean <hi>Cain</hi>) diſcontented, becauſe he approved of <hi>Abel</hi>'s Sacrifice, and not of his, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thee ſhall be his Deſire, and thou ſhalt rule over him,</hi> ſaid God to him in the ſame Language that he uſed to <hi>Eve</hi> concerning <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>'s Dominion over her: as if he ſhould have told him, that notwithſtanding the Goodneſs of his Brother's, and the Faultineſs of his own Religion, he would not take from him the Right of Dominion, which he had over him by Primogeniture. By the Rule of what I have ſaid, <hi>Adam</hi> was Univerſal Monarch of the Earth, and <hi>Cain</hi> ſhould have been ſo after him, if he ſurvived; but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55656:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>that he forfeited his Right of being ſo, together with his Life, by the Murder of his Brother; ſo it fell to <hi>Seth</hi> and his Family; upon which Account I put it, that <hi>Cainan,</hi> as the <hi>Arabian</hi> Writers ſay, was King of all the Earth; and that <hi>Abydenus</hi> and <hi>Beroſus</hi> reckon Ten Kings before the Flood, as there were Ten Generations from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Noah.</hi> However, <hi>Noah</hi> was by the Flood, put almoſt into the ſame Condition with <hi>Adam;</hi> therefore he is by an <hi>Eaſt-Indian</hi> Sect of Philoſophers, called <hi>The Second</hi> Adam. But it was not long before, if ſeveral of the Fathers were not miſinform'd, he parted the Earth by Lot, between his three Sons; by which means, the Inequality which was among all Mankind by Nature, as to Government, was in part broken. However, it is certain, that a Parity of Rule among many more Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, was brought in by the Diſperſion of <hi>Noah</hi>'s Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren at <hi>Babel,</hi> of which God was the Author of that extraordinary Oeconomy. But it was a Parity, not of all People of the ſame Society, but of ſeveral diſtinct Monarchs only: When God ſcattered the Race of Men, by the Confuſion of Tongues, it was not done with ſo much Confuſion, but that he took Order there ſhould be in every ſeperate Parcel of them, one who had a Right of Sovereignty over the reſt. We find in the Tenth Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> that God ſcattered them all by Families, and that of every Family there was a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or Head; and conſequently, one that was King of it, and a Founder of a Kingdom therein, and that He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary. This I could confirm of moſt of the Families and their Heads, there mentioned, by Humane Records; and that as well of thoſe that planted themſelves in <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern</hi> Climates, as of thoſe that ſate down in the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> and <hi>Southern;</hi> but it is not here convenient; God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thus took order, that Monarchy ſhould be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law of Nature, the Government of every ſeveral diſtinct Society of Men, which he conſtituted at
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55656:15"/>
               <hi>Babel,</hi> and that Succeſſively, it continued in Vogue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all Nations for at leaſt a Thouſand Years after that. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſays, That Anciently,<note place="margin">Ariſt. l. 1. Polit. Saluſt. in Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo Catilin. Cicero de Leg. lib. 3. Juſt. l. 1.</note> the Cities and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were under the Authority of Kings. The ſame is teſtified by <hi>Saluſt, Cicero, Juſtin,</hi> out of <hi>Trogus Pompei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and others; particularly of <hi>Greece,</hi> where there at length ſprang up ſo many Free Commonwealths, or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtocratical and Democratical States, <hi>Dyoniſſius Hali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnaſſeus</hi> aſſures us,<note place="margin">Dionyſ. Hal. l. 5.</note> that it was Originally Governed all by Kings. To come Home, <hi>Tacitus</hi> hath theſe Words of the <hi>Britains, Olim regibus parebant, nunc per Principes factionibus &amp; ſtudiis trahuntur.</hi> Indeed in all Records, whether of good or doubtful Credit, we find no Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in our Iſland, before we find a King. So little does it appear, that the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Kings derived their Scepters from the Hands of the People.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Monarchy only was the Government that God appointed to his People <hi>Iſrael.</hi> He, from their firſt coming out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> took the Government of them upon himſelf, and they came under a Theocracy. God therefore complains upon the Occaſion, in our Text, That they had rejected him, that he ſhould not Reign over them; and <hi>Samuel,</hi> that they ſaid, they would have a King, when the Lord their God was their King. This his Regency over them, he exerciſed by extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Methods, and immediate Diſpenſations; and he made <hi>Moſes, Joſhuah,</hi> and the Judges his Vice-Roys, who, though none of them had the Name of King, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Moſes,</hi> of whom it's ſaid, he was King in <hi>Jeſurun,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 33.5.</note> when the Heads of the People, and the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were gather'd together, they all exerciſed a Regal Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: But God did not intend that they ſhould have no other Mode of Government; he deſigned them, in due Seaſon, ſuch Kings as other Nations had. Beſides that, by the Spirit of God, <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid, <hi>The Scepter ſhall
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55656:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>not depart from</hi> Judah <hi>until</hi> Shiloh <hi>come:</hi> And <hi>Balaam,</hi> his King (ſpeaking of <hi>Iſrael</hi>) ſhall be higher than <hi>Agag,</hi> and his Kingdom ſhall be exalted; and the Mother of <hi>Samuel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 17.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhall give Strength unto his King, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt the Horn of his Annointed:</hi> Moſes ſaid from God, <hi>When thou art come into the Land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, and ſhalt poſſeſs it, and ſhalt dwell there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and ſhalt ſay, I will ſet a King over me, like as all the Nations that are about me, thou ſhalt in any wiſe ſet him over thee, whom the Lord thy God ſhall chuſe, one from among thy Brethren ſhalt thou ſet King over thee,</hi> &amp;c. The latter part of which words, may more Grammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally and properly, be render'd thus: <hi>Setting thou ſhalt ſet over thee a King, whom the Lord thy God ſhall chuſe; one from among thy Brethren ſhalt thou ſet King over thee;</hi> Or thus: <hi>Thou ſhalt, by all means, ſet over thee a King; him whom God ſhall chuſe from among thy Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ſhalt thou ſet King over thee.</hi> In this Sence the <hi>Syriack</hi> Verſion renders it. To the ſame purpoſe, the <hi>Targum</hi> of <hi>Ben. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziel, Ye ſhall ſeek Learning (or Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions) of the Lord, and after that ſhall ſet over you a King: It is not lawful to ſet a Stranger over you, who is not of your Brethren.</hi> Let us here, by the way, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, It is not ſaid, Thou ſhalt ſet under, but over, and the People are here ſpoken of in the Singular Number, as one Congregate Body: So that the King that ſhould be Conſtituted, was to be, to the whole imbodied So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, not an Inferior Miniſter, but a Superior Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. To this General Body of the People, God's Words are ſo far from allowing them a Liberty of ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up what Government they would, that they alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether deny it to them. Had God left them to chuſe whether they would ſet up Monarchy, or Ariſtocracy, or Democracy, or ſome Mixture of them, he would certainly have ſpoken of the reſt, as well as he does of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55656:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Firſt; but whereas he propounds to them only a King, and gives them Rules only about him; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſince no where in Scripture, God gives them any Meaſures for any other Supreme Governors or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is plain, he intended they ſhould have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Supreme Government, but that of a King. A true Paraphraſe of the Words take thus in ſhort; When you ſhall be well ſetled in your Habitations, and ſhall in a fitting manner declare your ſelves to have a mind to ſet over you Regal Government, but not any other, I am pleaſed that you ſhould, and by all means, you ſhall ſet over you that Government, but not any other; but then you ſhall ſet over you a King, whom I ſhall chuſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then he goes on, to give Rules for the King to obſerve, and concludes them thus: <hi>To the end that he may prolong his days in his Kingdom, he and his Children in the midſt of</hi> Iſrael; by which Words, God plainly expreſt what Good Will he had for a Kingdom, and that an Hereditary one, and for the Right Poſſeſſor of it and his Heirs; and how Advantageous the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance thereof would be to the People. According to this Sence of this place, the Maſters of <hi>Hebrew</hi> Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſay, that of three Commands which God gave the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to execute as ſoon as they were well ſettled in the Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> this was the Firſt, That they ſhould ſet a King over them. I ſhall only add on this Head, that the Throne of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chr. 29.33. 2. Chr. 13.8.</note> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The Throne of the Lord;</hi> and their Kingdom, <hi>The Kingdom of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, God in Scripture, declares himſelf in Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor of a Monarchy, ſet up by Force againſt a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, mix'd of Ariſtocracy and Democracy, and againſt the Wills of thoſe that were inveſted herewith. Such every one that is acquainted with Hiſtory, muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily believe the Government of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55656:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>to be: And yet the Holy Ghoſt gives the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror the Name of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> which was a Name of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, as appears by <hi>Macrobius</hi> calling the Dedicated Table in the Heathen Temples, where were their <hi>epulae libationes et ſtipes, Menſam Auguſtatam:</hi> And he gives that Name,<note place="margin">Luke 2.1. Acts 27.1. 1 Tim. 2.2. 1 Pet. 2.13.17.</note> not only to <hi>Caius Octavius,</hi> but alſo, if I take aim aright, to <hi>Nero;</hi> he gives either <hi>Claudius,</hi> or <hi>Nero,</hi> or both, the Name of King, which the Emperors for a long time ſhun'd, becauſe the <hi>Romans</hi> diſliked it, as ſignifying the Loſs of their Liberty.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.2.</note> He commands Prayers and Thanksgiving to be offer'd up for the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Emperor;<note place="margin">Rom. 13. 1 Pet. 2.13.17.</note> and as Tribute and Honor, ſo alſo Submiſſion to be paid to him; and this as Supreme, and for the Lord's Sake. He ſays alſo, in relation to him, when either <hi>Claudius</hi> or <hi>Nero</hi> wore the Diadem, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> the Powers, (the Authorities) that are at preſent exiſting, are ordained of God; and that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever reſiſted him, reſiſted the Ordinance of God, and that he was the Miniſter of God.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Kings are repreſented ſtanding in a much nearer Relation to God, than any other Secular Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours: But this is too full a Subject to be now diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, It is God's Charge to all, to have a moſt awful Reſpect for the King, and not to be of their Party who va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from it, or who enterpriſe any Alteration from Kingly Government: And this, by the Rule of having a moſt Awful Reſpect for the true God, and of not joyning with ſuch as vary from it; or as enterpriſe any Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from his Monarchy, they being Duties that are cloſely linked together; and becauſe haſty Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſuch ill Fortune, as no Body knows before-hand what it ſhall be, or perhaps will apprehend when it comes, certainly attend, and will unawares befall, as well the Sinners of the former ſort, as thoſe of the latter. So
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55656:17"/>muſt thoſe Words of <hi>Solomon</hi> be underſtood, <hi>My Son,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 24.21.</note> 
               <hi>fear thou the Lord, and the King, and meddle not with thoſe that are given to Change: For their Calamity ſhall riſe ſuddainly, and who knoweth the Ruine of them both?</hi> Both Changers from the Fear of the Lord, and Chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers from the Fear of the King.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, God ſpeaks of Regal Government, as alone juſtly agreable to the buſineſs of Government; which, in regard to thoſe that are to be Governed, is, that they may live a quiet and peaceable Life, in all Godlineſs and Honeſty; Godlineſs firſt, in paying God his Rights; then Honeſty: So far is <hi>ſalus Populi</hi> from being <hi>Suprema Lex.</hi> What leſs can we think, when we find it ſaid twice in the Book of <hi>Judges,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judge 17.6. &amp; 21.25.</note> 
               <hi>In thoſe days there was no King in Iſrael; but every man did that which was Right in his own Eyes;</hi> eſpecially conſidering what grievous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions then prevailed, and what impious and flagitious Enormities were then committed; in the Relations of ſome of which it is ſaid,<note place="margin">Judg. 18.1. &amp; 19.1.</note> 
               <hi>In thoſe days there was no King in Iſrael;</hi> a Signification, that they were to be aſcribed to the want of a King, though at the ſame time,<note place="margin">Judg. 21.16. Judg. 20.28.</note> there were both Elders of the Congregation, and a Renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed High-Prieſt. What leſs can we think, when we read in the ſame Book, <hi>They came to</hi> Laiſh, <hi>and ſaw the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that were therein, how they dwelt careleſs, after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, (by the Law) of the</hi> Zidonians, <hi>quiet and ſecure;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 18.7.</note> 
               <hi>and there was no Magiſtrate in the Land that might put them to Shame;</hi> conſidering unto what Miſchiefs we find them betrayed by that State of Affairs; and that the two words which we tranſlate Magiſtrate, properly denote an hereditary Poſſeſſor of Supreme Government: For to ſignifie ſuch a Government, is the word <hi>Eſar,</hi> uſed in Scripture, particularly in the Buſineſs of the Text; whence I cannot but think, came the <hi>Hetruſcan</hi> Word <hi>Aeſar,</hi> which ſignifies, the Supreme Governor of the World,<note place="margin">Suet. in Julii Caeſar. vit.</note>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:55656:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> God,<note place="margin">Heſych.</note> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Gods; and poſſibly the <hi>Greek</hi> Words, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a King. What leſs can we think when we find the want of a King, ſpoken of by God, as a grievous Calamity, and inflicted for the puniſhment of a People's Wickedneſs; When we read the Prophet <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah,</hi> complaining,<note place="margin">Lam. 4.20.</note> 
               <hi>The Breath of our Noſtrils, the anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Lord, was taken in their Nets, of whom we ſaid, under his Shadow we ſhall live among the Heathen.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 19.10, 11, 12, 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>Thy Mother is like a Vine,— ſhe had Rods for the Scepters of them that bear Rule;—but ſhe was plucked up in fury, ſhe was caſt down to the ground, and the</hi> Eaſt <hi>Wind dried up her Fruit; her ſtrong Rods were broken and withered, the fire conſumed them; and now ſhe is planted in the Wilderneſs, in a dry and thirſty Ground; and fire is gone out of a Rod of her Branches, which hath devoured her Fruit; ſo that ſhe hath no ſtrong Rod to be made a Scepter to Rule.</hi> And the Prophet <hi>Hoſea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 10.3.</note> 
               <hi>Now they ſhall ſay, we have no King, becauſe we feared not the Lord; what then ſhall a King do unto us?</hi> That is far from being inconſiderable, which <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Caſſius</hi> ſays,<note place="margin">Dion Caſſius Hiſt. Rom. <hi>l. 43.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocracy hath indeed a ſpecious Name, and ſeems by equal Laws, to give an equal portion to all; but it is argued by its Effects, not at all to agree with its Appellation: on the other ſide, Monarchy is harſh to the Ear, but moſt beneficial to the State: for it is eaſier to find one man good than many; and if ſome think it hard to find that one good man, they muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity think it impoſſible to find thoſe many: If then the one that governs is bad, he is yet rather to be choſen, than a great many like him. Of this, the Atcheivements of</hi> Greeks and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians, <hi>and of the</hi> Romans <hi>alſo, are Teſtimonies, they being always by far, better, and greater, and more, under Kings than under Populacy; and Grievances falling out leſs in Monarchies, than in Popular Governments. And if any Commonwealth hath flouriſh'd under a Popular Adminiſtration, it hath laſted but for a ſhort time, while they had not arrived at Greatneſs and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55656:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> Strength; ſo that there ſprang no Injuriouſneſs from Succeſs, nor Envy from Ambition. Abimelech,</hi> though I do not think he ſpake by immediate Inſpiration from Heaven, yet he did from the Oracle of Reaſon, and knew the Anſwer was obvious to a knowing Man, when he put that Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion to the <hi>Shechamites, Whether is it better for you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judges 9.2.</note> 
               <hi>either that threeſcore and ten Perſons Reign over you, or that one Reign over you?</hi> Be the State of a Nation never ſo like Heaven, ſeveral Suns, at the ſame time therein, will quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly turn it into a kind of Hell, by ſetting all on Fire.</p>
            <p>I ſhould ſay ſomething, by way of Application, and I have too large a Field for it; but neither the Time, nor the <hi>Times</hi> allow me Liberty to employ my ſelf therein: I muſt refer that, as <hi>Foelix</hi> did the hearing S. <hi>Paul,</hi> to a more convenient Seaſon. I ſhall at preſent only Conclude from what hath been ſaid, That Monarchy among men, is one of the faireſt Daughters of that of Heaven; and that they who have endeavor'd to deflower her, have thereby confeſs'd her Beauty; and heartily pray, that we may never think them good Chriſtians, whether Proteſtants, or Papiſts, who being Subjects, inſolently lay Hands on the Scepter, and attempt to Sway it; by which means, both that and the State, muſt needs ſuffer moſt untoward Convulſions; whoſe Tongues are Blaſphemouſly, and their Fingers Sacrilegiouſly buſie, with both Monarchy and Monarchs; who would eſtabliſh Iniquity againſt Kings by a Law: And that whereas the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were guilty of a great Wickedneſs in asking a King in that manner that they did, we may never be of a greater, in ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no King, or ſuch an one as imports little more; but that God would always preſerve his Government, both in State and Church; ſo that no Man may be ſo horribly wicked, as to arrogate to himſelf the Prerogative of doing what God is ſaid to have done,<note place="margin">Lam. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>deſpiſing in the Indignaation of his Anger, the King and the Prieſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
